<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Monsieur Jvriev's judgment upon the question of defending our religion by arms, with reflections upon the affairs of England, in his ninth pastoral letter of the third year faithfully translated out of French.</title>
            <title>Lettres pastorales addressées aux fidèles de France qui gémissent sous la captivité de Babylon. Année 3. Lettre 9. English</title>
            <author>Jurieu, Pierre, 1637-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15972</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12724880</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12724880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46363)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 694:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Monsieur Jvriev's judgment upon the question of defending our religion by arms, with reflections upon the affairs of England, in his ninth pastoral letter of the third year faithfully translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>Lettres pastorales addressées aux fidèles de France qui gémissent sous la captivité de Babylon. Année 3. Lettre 9. English</title>
                  <author>Jurieu, Pierre, 1637-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ..., and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Translation of Lettres pastorales addressées aux fidèles de France qui gémissent sous la captivité de Babylon, année 3, lettre 9.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66305:1"/>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               </hi>'s Judgment Upon the Queſtion of <hi>Defending our Religion by Arms,</hi> WITH REFLECTIONS UPON THE <hi>Affairs of England,</hi> IN HIS Ninth Paſtoral LETTER of the Third Year.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated out of</hi> French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed, and Entered according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> next the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bayly.</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:66305:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66305:2"/>
            <head>THE Tranſlator TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>'TIS ſaid by the Prophet <hi>Daniel, That many ſhall run to and fro, and knowledge ſhall be encreaſed:</hi> The Commerce of Nations, the Tranſlating from one Language to another, is this running to and fro, whereby Mankind communicate their general Sentiments, improve by the Correſpondence, and are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved from the Curſe of <hi>Babel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>People that only <hi>meaſure themſelves by themſelves, and compare themſelves among themſelves,</hi> take very ſcanty meaſures, and make very fond compariſons: when they are miſtaken, they have no way of rectifying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but enjoy a very great ſatisfaction in being poſitive and immovable, tho' they are never ſo much in the wrong.</p>
            <p>In oppoſition to this, the World has always had a great deference to a Catholick Sence; ſo ſoon as ever Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enjoyed its liberty under the Glorious Emperour <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> there was ſuch an aſſembling of Councils, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating the Judgment of particular Churches for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of the whole, that the Heathens were wont to
<pb facs="tcp:66305:3"/>deride the Chriſtians for tiring the Post-horſes, and wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Stage-Coaches of the Empire.</p>
            <p>When Chriſtianity was Tranſubſtantiated into Popery, and all the Methods of Religion turn'd against it ſelf, then was Catholiciſm made uſe of as the grand Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of its own Ruine: The general <hi>falling away,</hi> which was the Prediction of a falſe Religion prevailing was the chief argument, why that Religion was not falſe which had prevailed.</p>
            <p>So that we have the Judgment both of Friends and Enemies, thoſe who first ſetled Religion, and thoſe who afterwards overthrew it, that the general Opinion of the Church of God ought to be of the greatest eſteem, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in thoſe difficult Caſes, where we are not our ſelves able to determine our Duties out of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>'Tis then only diſputed, which is the Catholick Church; that which ſhone bright immediately after our Saviour's time, or that prevailing Faction of Apoſtates which cloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Heavens, and cast a mist over the face of the Earth? But the Light of Truth is ſo ſprung forth again, that the Queſtion vaniſhes; 'tis eaſy to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Day and Night.</p>
            <p>Now if the Chriſtians had ſo great an Opinion of their common Agreement, before their Religion was corrupted, why ſhould not we honour the ſame way? And, ſince Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is but the Reſtoration of Primitive Religion, be glad to hear what foreign Churches ſay of thoſe Doctrines which are diſputed amongst us.</p>
            <p>He is an Enemy to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who would ſet it up against the Reform'd Churches of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and of the <hi>Northern</hi> Crowns, where God is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped alſo after the manner which his Enemies call Hereſy: Why ſhould not the Church of God be eſteemed one Catholick Church ſince its Reformation as well as before its grand Depravation? There were as many Hereſies and Schiſms
<pb facs="tcp:66305:3"/>and Errours within its bowels then as now, but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Agreement of the greater part in ſubſtantial Truths, made the Advice of one Church to another, to be very much reverenced and regarded.</p>
            <p>The Judgment of Monſieur <hi>Jurieu</hi> is not to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as his private Opinion, but as the general Sence of the good Chriſtians of <hi>France;</hi> for the Papiſts had an Intrigue to deſtroy the whole Reform'd Religion all over <hi>Europe,</hi> by perſwading the Proteſtants to ſtand ſtill while they were ruined; and to this purpoſe Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> picks up and ridicules the Deciſions of their Synods, <hi>That it was lawful to make uſe of Arms in favour of Religion.</hi> So that this is a Defence of their ancient Doctrine, and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuing the Right of Self-preſervation from the hands of their Enemies, in a most needful time when they would have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it away from all men, in order to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Truth. Certainly the <hi>French</hi> have demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch eminent Loyalty and Patience, that they well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be heard upon the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>We may in <hi>England</hi> look back with ſome horror upon the danger we have eſcaped; this piece of Policy was framed alſo for the finest and ſtrongest Intrigue that could bring about our Deſtruction; it was the preſumption of Arbitrary and Irreſiſtible Power, of Abſolute and undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Obedience, which heartned our Enemies to ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, as they durſt not otherwiſe have thought upon.</p>
            <p>They had the advantage of many Years to make prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, by preferring ſuch to Places of Honour and Power, who were themſelves generally the greatest Slaves, and ſo were willing to enſlave others. The choice was made with a great deal of Judgment and Curioſity; either of ſuch whoſe Atheiſm and Debauchery made them ready to do any thing, or of ſuch who had ſuffer'd under the Pretenders to Liberty, and therefore were inclined to an exceſs of Duty.</p>
            <p>The former run into all the extravagancies of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb facs="tcp:66305:4"/>having their mouths full of great ſwelling words, <hi>That the King was above Jeſus Chriſt; that Tyranny and Oppreſſion themſelves, if acted by Perſons in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, were the Ordinances of God, and not to be reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under pain of Damnation.</hi> But Death has eaſed ſome places of their burdens, and called thoſe Followers of <hi>Balaam</hi> before a Tribunal, where they ſhall behold him whom they pierced.</p>
            <p>The better part conſider'd the Glories of ſuffering Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how much it was able to bear, and that Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had first made its triumphant entry into the World; they therefore encouraged the inferiour Clergy to ſuch a degree, that it was almost received as the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited Authority was of Divine Right; and that tho' Religion was never ſo much our Property, yet it had a property in it, to yield up itſelf and every thing elſe to the will of the first Invader.</p>
            <p>But ſo ſoon as the Rights of our Religious and Civil Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties were found to be mortally wounded, and that its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest was to be deſtroyed by ſuch Sufferings as neither the Laws of God or Man required, then could the Fathers of the Church no longer conceal a Truth, the neglect whereof had near cost them, that which was dearer to them than their Lives; the tenderneſs they bore to their Children would not expoſe them to an unneceſſary Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>After their perſonal Sufferings, and the Day-break of our Deliverance appear'd, the late King <hi>James</hi> was alarm'd with an expreſſion in the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Declaration, <hi>That he was moſt earneſtly Invited hither by divers of the Lords both Spiritual and Temporal, and by many Gentlemen and others.</hi> He therefore ſent for the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>London, Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> and <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> to ſign an Abhorrence under their hands of the intended Invaſion.</p>
            <p>But this they refuſed to do; not being able to give up
<pb facs="tcp:66305:4"/>a Church, which by the Providence of God was by Law eſtabliſhed, and which they had the Care of committed to them: They durst not diſcountenance a Deliverance which (every body was then ſenſible) was ſo divinely offer'd, and wherein all the Proteſtant Intereſt of <hi>Europe</hi> was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked. This Refuſal the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> has lately publiſhed, and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> has favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Licenſe under his own hand.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the late King <hi>James</hi> had thrown up the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, cancell'd the Writs of Parliament, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf from the Kingdom, then did the Archbiſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>Wincheſter, St. Aſaph, Ely, Rocheſter,</hi> and <hi>Peterborough,</hi> with the Lords Temporal that were about <hi>London,</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> devolv'd themſelves upon the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> acknowledging his <hi>great Kindneſs, his v<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, his Hazard to Reſcue them from Popery and Slavery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Convocations of <hi>England</hi> had formerly aſſiſted the foreign Proteſtants both with their Prayers and Purſes, now was the happy day of Retribution come, when we were to eat that Bread which was caſt upon the Waters an hundred Years before; It had been a renouncing of the ancient Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the old Charity laid up in ſtore for us, if we had not accepted ſo great a Deliverance.</p>
            <p>The common pertneſs of young Divines, and the invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate prejudice of ſome elder, will not be able to rencounter the more ancient Judgment, and this late authentick Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> It will be ſatisfaction to behold here the concurrence of a foreign Church, for we have always valued Catholiciſm; but now we much more deſire it, now we are under the Head of the Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and hope that our preſent Soveraign of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> will be another <hi>Britiſh Conſtantine</hi> to the World. Thoſe Churches which never had the Favour of Princes, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:66305:5"/>but want many advantages, and we who were Reform'd by a Prince, who did not only ſhake off the Pope's <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but reſerved ſeveral of them to himſelf, are capable of being made more happy.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that have travell'd abroad, and ſearcht the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieves of the Proteſtant Churches, find how the principal Reformers and Eſtabliſhers of our Religion conſulted them, and how greivouſly they were afflicted to be over-ruled by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Men in the Eſtabliſhment of thoſe things which were not to be found in the Catholiciſm of the Reform'd Religion.</p>
            <p>And we have ſadly found the miſchief thereof, for men who are the Authors and Abettors of thoſe things, which are particular to themſelves, are apt to be more fond of their own Inſtitutions, than of the Catholick and Divine Ordinances; and ſo the zeal of a particular Church has been in danger of ſpending it ſelf without being concern'd for, and ſometimes in oppoſition to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal.</p>
            <p>As I began with one Prophet ſo I'll conclude with another; let <hi>Iſaiah</hi> now revive us with an Aſſurance, that God will at laſt give <hi>Kings to be Nurſing-fathers, and Queens to be Nurſing-mothers to his Church.</hi> And ſuch as we now have, <hi>England</hi> never had before.</p>
            <p>He hath propheſied alſo, <hi>That the light of the Moon ſhall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun ſhall be ſeven-fold, as the light of ſeven days, in the day that the Lord bindeth up the breach of his people, and healeth the ſtroke of their wound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſuch a litteral accompliſhment of this, that 'tis hard not to believe it the deſign of the place; we have ſuch a ſeven fold influence of our Sun to revive and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the diſtreſſed part of the World, and our Moon is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually Soveraign with him. Shall not all this make us happy, the greateſt Authority and the beſt Examples? if not, 'tis becauſe we are the worſt People that ever enjoy'd the Sun ſhine.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66305:5"/>
            <head>THE Ninth <hi>Paſtoral Letter</hi> of the Third Year, Wherein this Queſtion is Examined, <hi>Whether it be Lawful to Defend our Religion by Arms?</hi> WITH REFLECTIONS UPON THE <hi>Affairs of England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Our moſt Dear Brethren, Grace and Peace be given to you by our God and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE did in our laſt leave Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Boſſuet</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring with all his might to overthrow Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Burnet,</hi> by making him contradict himſelf; he was alſo labouring to render the Reformation of <hi>England</hi> Odious, and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſome Variations upon the Article of the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>But theſe Variations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid aſide, and reſerv'd for Volumes, and perhaps
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66305:6"/>for future Ages, Mr. <hi>Boſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuet</hi> in the remaining part of his tenth Book enters upon the Wars of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>The conſpiracy of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiſe</hi> comes upon the Stage, dreſt up with I don't know how many Reflections, and as many Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to prove, that it ought entirely to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the <hi>Huguenots,</hi> and had no other cauſe but Religion.</p>
            <p>All the Civil Wars of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Age are made to re-appear; both the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſination of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> before <hi>Orleans</hi> by <hi>Poltrot,</hi> and that of. the Preſident <hi>Minard</hi> by <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art</hi> are remembred.</p>
            <p>And amongſt all this are inſerted ſome Deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Synods, and other Arguments to prove that the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> think well of maintaining the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by Arms.</p>
            <p>All this fine parcel of Hiſtory is compoſed of many matters of Fact, and one queſtion of Right. The Fact relates to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Wars of the laſt Age, upon which it is not here my buſineſs to diſcourſe, an Anſwer may be given, if it be thought requiſite; and for me, that which hath been already ſaid in my Anſwer to the Jeſuit <hi>Mainburg</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſm,</hi> may be ſufficient.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion of Right is concerned in the taking up, and uſing Arms for the Defence of Religion, which Monſieur <hi>Boſſuet</hi> propoſes as a great Crime in the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>For ſince the Goſpel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges no other Arms but thoſe that are Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, the Church is not to attempt any thing but by the Word, nor to defend itſelf but by Patience.</p>
            <p>Thus the Primitive Chriſtians defended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; we cannot find that they repell'd force by force: Their Prayers and their Tears were the only Bucklers they oppoſed to the Violence of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors: but behold now a new ſort of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, of Reformers of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66305:6"/>Church and the World, who take up Arms, that they may repel the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences of others by Violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their own.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the fine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places wherewith the Proteſtants of all <hi>Europe</hi> are at this day entertain'd, to perſwade them that they ought patiently, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Emotion, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the utmoſt Efforts of Popery to their Ruin.</p>
            <p>The circumſtances of the preſent time oblige us to enlarge a little upon this Queſtion; not only in way of Anſwer to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> and his Friends, but principally with a deſign to ſatisfie ſome who are truly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious, and not well inſtructed as to the ſenſe of this Maxim, <hi>That it is not lawful to make uſe of Arms in favour of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, does it not well become <hi>M.</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> and in general the whole Papiſtry to raiſe the Reputation of this Maxim, that the Conduct of the Proteſtants might be rendred Odious? The Papiſtry, I ſay, which may be review'd in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as an unchain'd Fury, carrying a Sword in one hand, and Fire in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, filling <hi>Europe</hi> with Deſolations, and bathing the Earth with Bloud, to Eſtabliſh and Defend it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>But it is not lawful to employ our Arms in Defence of our Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, why then did the Papiſtry endeavou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant Chriſtianity in the Eaſt, by ſo many millions of People under the Badge of the Croſs? Why were Wars waged expreſly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of holy Wars? Why did the Popes (to eſtabliſh the Authority, they pretend to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Jeſus Chriſt) bring Deſolation upon <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope?</hi> Why did they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne Emperours and Kings? Why have they raiſed Arms, and bid Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles? Why have they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged the Father againſt the Son, and the Son a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Father? Why
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66305:7"/>have they imployed the Armies of the Croſs, to maſſacre an hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigenſes?</hi> Why does the Tribunal of the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion find Imployment for Hangmen, Fires, Tortures, Executions in favour of Religion?</p>
            <p>Why, when the Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry would firſt ſet its Foot in any place, does it run to Arms with the utmoſt Fury? Why to advance it ſelf does it make uſe of the moſt Abominable Crimes, Aſſaſſinations, Treaſons, Poyſonings of the neareſt Relations, and Benefactors themſelves, burning of Cities, Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Shams, and other ſuch like Actions, of which both ancient and modern Hiſtories are able to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us with Examples?</p>
            <p>Why does Papiſtry im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy Dragoons, and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to violate Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to make People deny a Religion which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be true, and to embrace that which they believe to be falſe; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by conſtraining them to Prophane and Sacrilegious Communions?</p>
            <p>Certainly 'tis a great fineneſs of Wit for Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> to retail this ſevere Maxim in the preſent juncture, <hi>That it is not lawful to employ our Arms in Defence of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Gentlemen might have been happy in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring themſelves with ſo fine a peice of Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if their Conduct had left no ſuch Footſteps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind: But now the Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Exceſſes are ſo far from allowing themſelves a juſtification, that they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven take away any right of inſulting over their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
            <p>But without all this Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> is to know, that we are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to have ſeveral de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions found in our Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods from whence a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion may be drawn, that according to us, it is not always forbidden to make uſe of Arms in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Religion.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66305:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An Abbot is applauded for this, that he bore Arms to maintain the Goſpel.</hi> Mr. <hi>Boſſuet</hi> has found it in the National Synod of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> 1563, and he has made it to be printed in Capital Letters, for the greater remark, and that it might be an Eternal Diſgrace up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the Party.</p>
            <p>What extravagancy of Thought was this in a time, and in a Kingdom, where ſo many Souldiers and Officers bear Arms, not to <hi>maintain</hi> the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, but to plant Popery in the Hearts of the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is then very neceſſary to diſtinguiſh between <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing</hi> Religion, and <hi>Defending</hi> of it. And it is certain, that the Chriſtian Morals do not permit the Eſtabliſhment of Religion by Arms. I have no need to prove it, the thing is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident of its ſelf, and there can hardly be found any people that dare im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugn this Truth; and from hence I conclude, that Popery is really Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, the Antipodes of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>I know not any other Religion in the World, which forces People by Fire and Sword to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their own Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of that which is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet</hi> hath enlarged his Empire by Arms, and the enlargement of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire hath conduced very much to the enlargement of his Religion: But we do not ſee at laſt, that the <hi>Califs</hi> and <hi>Mahometan</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have put the Knife to the Throats of Chriſtians, to make them abjure Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and to embrace Mahometaniſm, it is true, the Chriſtian Religion has periſhed under their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; but by Poverty, and Meanneſs, and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Ignorance, to which they had reduced the Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The Glory of <hi>Planting</hi> Chriſtianity by Arms has been due to Popery, and its Princes.</p>
            <p>But to <hi>Defend</hi> Religion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66305:8"/>by Arms is another thing, and there is neither Reaſon nor Authority by which it can be proved to be a Crime. All the World is agreed that Defence is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and allowed by the Laws of Nature, to which the poſitive Laws of God never made any Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>It is then lawful to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ones Life, ones Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, one's Wife, ones Children, ones Country, and ones Goods by Arms; and is it not lawful to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ones Religion by the ſame means?</p>
            <p>I would fain be ſhewed a little from whence the difference ariſes, and who it is who hath ſo diſarm'd the Religion, as to leave it expoſed to the Violence of the firſt comer?</p>
            <p>This Maxim is proved falſe by the common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all Mankind, ſince a Maxim contrary to it has paſſed into a Proverb, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad aras, even to the Altars,</hi> we ſay, which is as much as to confeſs that Complaiſance and Patience ſhould take place in all things but Altars and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>If this Maxim be true, it muſt be ſo Univerſally, or elſe the Exceptions ought to be made known to us: If this Maxim, <hi>That it is unlawful to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Religion by Arms,</hi> be true without Exception, it follows, that an Army of <hi>Turks</hi> invading our Frontiers, and over-ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Provinces, only for the Eſtabliſhment of their Religion, and for the Ruin of ours, it will be unlawful for us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelves. If they do but ſay, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire neither our Goods, nor our Liberties, nor our Country; but only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of us, to receive their Religion, and quit our own, becauſe there ſhall be no other Intereſt in this Demand, but only that of Religion, therefore we muſt preſently lay down our Arms, admit Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metaniſm, of at leaſt be content to ſuffer Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66305:8"/>
            <p>Is it not lawful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſuch Violence by Arms? Who dares ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance ſuch an Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance!</p>
            <p>Our Children, our Goods, and even our Country ought to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifie'd for Religion, when it is neceſſary for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it; and I ſhall not dare to defend my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by the ſame means by which I ſhould defend my temporal Intereſts. This may be ſufficient to make it apparent, that the Maxim is falſe, if taken without any exception.</p>
            <p>Now, if there muſt be exceptions, let them be ſet forth; here we ſhall not fail of being told, that it is unlawful to Defend our Religion by Arms, when it is attackt by the lawful Soveraigns of the State. But is this agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Conſciences of the Papiſts, who make it ſo criminal in us, that we will not abandon our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to the Injuſtice and Violences of Soveraigns; dare they affirm, that they are diſpoſed to ſuffer the utmoſt upon this account?</p>
            <p>If their Kings in the moſt Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould endeavour to plant, I don't ſay <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometaniſm</hi> or <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> by deſtroying <hi>Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but <hi>Lutheraniſm</hi> or <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſm</hi> by Violence, would they ſuffer it, and believe themſeves oblig'd to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy no other Arms but Tears, and Patience, and Martyrdom?</p>
            <p>I can't tell whether they would dare to ſay ſo; they dare ſay any thing according to the diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Times and Intereſts; but we know very well, that if they ſhould dare to ſay ſo, it would be a lye; for it 'tis certain, there is no ſort of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence which they have not made uſe of to arreſt the deſigns of ſuch a Prince, and deprive him of his Life. We cannot take one ſtep in the Hiſtory of Papiſm, without finding proofs, but 'tis needleſs to report them.</p>
            <p>Kings are not Maſters
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66305:9"/>of Conſcience and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they are not ſo much as Maſters of the Lives of their Subjects, how then ſhould they be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and their Religion?</p>
            <p>All thoſe who are not devoted to Flattery, do avow, that the right of <hi>Self-Preſervation</hi> is a right which cannot be aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: a People hath always right to take care of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by all manner of ways, againſt a Tyrant who would ruin and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Soveraign for ſome worldly Intereſt, for the refuſal of Tribute or Homage, or in an Humor, ſhould reſolve upon Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacring a whole Nation, or one great party, is there any one ſo much a Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, as to aſſert, that ſuch a Soveraign has right to do it, and that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have no right to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch Violence with Force?</p>
            <p>Such an one will be confuted by all Mankind, for 'tis believed by every one, that he has a right to uſe all means for his own preſervation, when he is ſet upon by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Violence.</p>
            <p>Having made this Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, let us make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; Suppoſe a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign ſhould attempt to Maſſacre his Subjects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall this cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which intervenes, tye the hands of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, annihilate the Laws of Nature, deprive them of the inalienable Right of Self-Preſervation? Shall it be lawful for a People to preſerve and defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they are to be maſſacred for refuſing unjuſt Taxes, and ſhall it not be lawful to defend themſelves when they are to be maſſacred upon the account of Religion?</p>
            <p>I muſt ſay this is a ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh piece of Morality: let him that deſires to lye at the Foot ſtool of a Throne, and flatter Kings, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it; no man will ever really believe it.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:66305:9"/>
            <p>'Tis of no great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to argue upon the Rights of Soveraigns; 'tis a queſtion we will not enter upon. But thus much we ought to know, That the Rights of GOD, the Rights of the People, and the Rights of Kings are inſeparable: This good ſence demonſtrates, and therefore a Prince that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilates the Right of GOD and the Right of the People, does there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by annihilate his own Right.</p>
            <p>Nothing is due to him who pays nothing to any one, neither to God nor men.</p>
            <p>The Suppoſition we make, is not a Caſtle in the Air; and, without ſpeaking of Princes called Chriſtian (who have maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred their Subjects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) the Hiſtory of the Church preſents us with <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> who enterpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the extirpation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians by an univerſal Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre: Where is it to be found in the Goſpel, that the Chriſtian-Subjects of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire had no right to oppoſe this Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; whereas, if for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other cauſe than that of Religion, their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours had oppreſſed them in ſuch a manner, they might have had right to defend themſelves? If this be ſo, Religion is of the meaneſt concern in the World.</p>
            <p>If the whole World had courage enough to ſuffer Martyrdom, the Spiritual Intereſt of Religion would not be ſo deeply concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but when 'tis to be conſider'd, that in a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of Chriſtians, perhaps not ten Thouſand of them are ſo diſpoſed as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure maſſacring, we are to recollect, that ſuch an expoſing the Truth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the Faithful to the dangers of Apoſtaſie, gives up an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the Weaker to ruin, and ſuffers the whole Church to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>If this be ſo, that 'tis always unlawful to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66305:10"/>the True Religion by Arms, wherefore is the Memory of the <hi>Maccabees</hi> ſo bleſſed in the Church? Why are they not accurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Wiſe? Why are they applauded for having taken Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings of <hi>Syria,</hi> their lawful Soveraigns? The Perſecution of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Antiochus</hi> was meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the account of Religion: for the <hi>Jews</hi> were very ſubmiſſive both in their Tribute and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Homage: But he would oblige them to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure their Religion, for which many ſuffer'd Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom with admirable Patience. The <hi>Maccabees</hi> had alſo the ſame way to ſignalize their courage; but they took another way, they took up Arms, they defended their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they ſhook off the Yoke of the Kings of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> not only as to their Spiritual but their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Bondage.</p>
            <p>An exact preſident for the States of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> in the laſt Age, who having taken up Arms firſt to maintain their Religion, then ſhook off the temporal Yoke of <hi>Spain,</hi> and made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a ſeparate State.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> and his Friends, who ſo bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſure the <hi>Hollanders</hi> for taking Arms upon the account of their Religion, and for having taken that occaſion to ſhake off an inſupportable Yoke, ought to make out the difference between the caſe of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> and that of the <hi>Low Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is incumbent upon him, who ſo furiouſly ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies our Synods for recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending an Abbot <hi>who bore Arms in defence of the Goſpel,</hi> to draw an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thoſe grand Hero's of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, whom all Chriſtians ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, and whoſe Conduct they approve.</p>
            <p>But there is now an Objection fram'd from the Conduct of the Primitive Chriſtians, who during the ten Perſecutions never ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66305:10"/>their Perſecutors with any thing but Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. God forbid, that I ſhould diminiſh their Worth, or abate any thing of thoſe Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are due to them: but I want to be inſtructed, how they were in a condition to provide againſt the Violences of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours.</p>
            <p>I don't know that the Chriſtians were as one to five hundred, if you take the whole extent of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire: There are Authors that believe <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf could not number above forty thouſand Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the ſecond and third Ages; whereas in the laſt accounts, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were reckon'd to riſe to many Millions. If then there were ſo few in the capital City, how could there be ſo great an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in other places? How then could ſo ſmall a number of People, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd thorough the extent of ſo vaſt an Empire, maintain themſelves, where there were numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies on foot to guard their ſpacious Frontiers? 'Twas not then onely Religion but Prudence in the firſt Chriſtians to ſuffer a leſs evil to avoid a greater: if they had opened them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a ſtate of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, they had been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpos'd to inevitable Death, ſo that they had no other way but to conceal them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> is cited upon this occaſion, who reports that the Chriſtians fill'd the Cities, the Caſtles, the Armies; but 'tis known that <hi>Tertullian</hi> was an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, and amplified things more than ever any Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Church did. It would be a very hard thing to make good all he hath ventur'd upon.</p>
            <p>But, there is ſomething elſe very conſiderable as to the conduct of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians in the point of taking Arms: there were many then who believed it altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to uſe the Sword upon any occaſion, either in War or Judgment for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66305:11"/>the puniſhment of Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. This was an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Opinion, a Maxim generally acknowledged to be falſe at this day; ſo that Patience was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an Errour, and a piece of Morality not well underſtood.</p>
            <p>At the bottom, it was not this fineneſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which hindred the firſt Chriſtians to defend themſelves againſt their Perſecutors: for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votional Perſons, whoſe Morality was ſo ſevere, were a ſmall number in compariſon to others. And by the complaints which the Fathers make of the Chriſtians Manners in their Age; it is eaſie to collect, that ſo many Chriſtians, being then ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular in the other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their lives, did not ſuffer themſelves to be maſſacred for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, but becauſe they were impotent and indefenſible.</p>
            <p>Yet ſuppoſe the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians did meerly out of tenderneſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience neglect to defend themſelves, it ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, they did not do ill: and yet it does not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that thoſe who do not imitate them do ill. For 'tis always lawful to remit ones right; a man may do with his own what he will: yet another man does not ſin, becauſe he will maintain his right.</p>
            <p>'Tis a very high degree of Regeneration, to quit ones Goods to an unjuſt Invader, for avoiding of Reſiſtance: but ſtill thoſe who have not advanced ſo far in their Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are not in a ſtate of Sin.</p>
            <p>There is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>better</hi> and <hi>well: He that giveth his Virgin in marriage doth well; but he that giveth her not in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage doth better.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe then theſe Chriſtians did <hi>better</hi> in not taking up Arms to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Perſecution, it does not follow, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may do <hi>well,</hi> though they do otherwiſe, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66305:11"/>perhaps <hi>better</hi> in their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Another Objection is found out in the words of our Saviour: <hi>Whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on the right cheek, turn to him the other alſo. And if any man will ſue thee at the law, and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloak alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> It muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt deſigned this for particular perſons, not for Societies and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: 'tis an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance to maintain, that Societies, and States, and Kingdoms are obliged to ſubmit themſelves to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very unjuſt Oppreſſor, that does Invade them. Private perſons for the publick peace do well to obſerve this direction of Jeſus Chriſt: but for the publick good, Governors of States are obliged to act otherwiſe. Now the Church is a Corporation, a Society, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ought to preſerve her Aſſemblies, and her Subjects, and to do it in all thoſe ways which are lawful by the right of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and of Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Our Saviour there ſpeaks of worldly Intereſts, not of ſacred things and Religion: Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt never bid us quit our Religion, our Temples, our Altars, to him that would raviſh them from us; but to part with our Coat and our Cloak. There is no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of conſequence from the one to the other.</p>
            <p>Certainly our Lord ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had any deſign to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the proceedings of Juſtice into Crimes; when a man endeavour'd to run under covert from the violent perſuits of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vader that would take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Goods from him: Chriſtian Morality never puſh'd on Severity at ſuch a rate. If then, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this Precept of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, it is permitted by the Laws of the Goſpel to reſiſt an unjuſt Oppreſſour that would take away our Goods from us; by much
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66305:12"/>ſtronger reaſon is this Commandment far from prejudicing our right of defending Religion by Arms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> This Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſo far from fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring ſuch extravagant Morality, that it gives no countenance to it; for in this paſſage our Saviour ſets forth how far our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience is oblig'd: 'Tis that we ſuffer moderate Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, a box o'th' ear, tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable loſſes, as to be rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of a Cloak, or ſuch temporal Goods, whoſe preſervation was not equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to the loſs of our Peace: but he does not ſay, if any one would take away thy Life, don't de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it. So that take our Saviour's words in the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt rigour, he hath not left it unlawful for a man to defend his Life.</p>
            <p>Now if it be lawful for a man to defend his Life againſt Tyrants, that would take it away for temporal reaſons; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee why it may not be lawful to defend it when they would murder us upon the account of Religion. We ought then to ſuffer even to the laſt extremity, but this extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is come when they would raviſh from us that which is more dear than Life it ſelf, our Religion and our Eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Another Argument, for maintaining this piece of ſevere Morality, that we ought not to take up Arms for the defence of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is drawn from the words of Jeſus Chriſt to his Diſciples upon the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> denying him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: The Diſciples ſaid to our Lord, <hi>Wilt thou that we command fire to come down from heaven, and conſume them even as Elias did.</hi> The Lord an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them. <hi>Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of; for the Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what does this ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie? You ſhall have it in a word, that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lawful to open a way
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66305:12"/>for Jeſus Chriſt to enter by force, nor to eſtabliſh the Goſpel by Arms: but if the <hi>Samaritans</hi> had come to a Houſe that belong'd to Jeſus Chriſt, or any of his Diſciples, would have driven them out of it and diſpoſſed them, think you that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt would have order'd his Diſciples to be gone and ſeek a lodging ſome where elſe? I ſee nothing like it.</p>
            <p>For once again, there is a vaſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Attacking</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending:</hi> The Goſpel has not taken away from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man the right of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending himſelf againſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Aggreſſors.</p>
            <p>And this without doubt our Saviour intended, when he was walking in the Garden, where he knew the <hi>Jews</hi> would come and ſeize him by violence; he then order'd his Diſciples that he who had a Sword ſhould take it: and when one ſaid, <hi>Behold, here are two Swords,</hi> he anſwered, <hi>it is enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was not enough to repel the violence he was to meet withal, for two armed men were not able to oppoſe the armed Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, that accompanied <hi>Judas;</hi> but it was enough for his purpoſe, to let his Diſciples know, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch an occaſion they had a right to defend themſelves with Arms.</p>
            <p>For otherwiſe what ſence can there be in this, Take your Swords: of what uſe could they be if they might not defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? It is true, that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt commanded St. <hi>Peter</hi> to put up his Sword into his Sheath; and he healed the <hi>Ear of Malchus:</hi> But by this he gives us to underſtand, that tho' he has right to repel force with force, yet he would have his Diſciples make uſe of it only as a proper time and occaſion may require. And he there gives the reaſon of it: 'tis becauſe <hi>that</hi> ought to be accompliſh'd which was ordained by the Father. And that which he adds
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66305:13"/>to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> when he bid him put up his Sword in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sheath, <hi>viz All they that take the Sword ſhall periſh by the Sword,</hi> cannot ſignifie that uſing the Sword is always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, or chiefly when it is employed upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Religion, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not I ſay, ſignifie any thing like it: For,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, 'tis falſe; ſince there are an hundred occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, where the uſe of the Sword is notoriouſly known to be lawful.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, Jeſus Chriſt would have contradicted himſelf upon the very ſpot; for there he ſays, <hi>Let him that hath a Sword, take it: Behold two, it is enough.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>So that this muſt ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that he who ſtrikes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly with the Sword, ſhall periſh by the Sword. Now one may ſtrike unjuſtly with the Sword upon theſe two accounts, either when he does it that he has no right, or when this right is made uſe of upon ſome occaſion that is not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Pleaſure of God. St. <hi>Peter</hi> had not uſed his Sword in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeaſon; not but that he had a right, which it was not then a time to exerciſe, for then God would have Jeſus Chriſt die, and St. <hi>Peter</hi> ought to have underſtood it.</p>
            <p>In a word, Jeſus Chriſt commanded to take the Sword, for eſtabliſhing the Right which the Church has to defend herſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt unjuſt Oppreſſors; and he forbid <hi>Peter</hi> to ſtrike, to teach the Church, that ſhe ought to ſubmit when God has made known his Will, that ſhe muſt ſuffer.</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Boſſuet</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent defender of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Moral, That <hi>we are forbidden to maintain the Goſpel by Arms,</hi> finds our Morality to looſe in this point, he will do well to call into his help for our Correction, <hi>Eſcobar, Tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourin, Caramuel,</hi> and all the Tribe of new Caſuiſts, who are very good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and as good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks as they are, make it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66305:13"/>lawful to kill a Man for a Crown-piece, or an Apple.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs we have no deſign at all to inſpire with the ſentiments of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, thoſe who have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd ſo cruel a Perſecution in <hi>France</hi> upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Religion. God forbid, we do on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary render thanks to God, that not one of them has been prevail'd upon to do any Action of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; for though they could not have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed others, without having been deſtroyed themſelves, yet it is a ſurprizing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that among ſo many people of different Characters, there ſhould not be found a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who would act the part of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> to bury themſelves, and their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies under the ſame Ruins, which was eaſie for them to have done. But the Patience where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they have ſuffer'd is an Argument that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God hath ſuſtained them in their Calamities.</p>
            <p>Nor do we pretend here to make a defence for all the Wars which have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken upon the account of Religion, nor all thoſe which were for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of a good Religion.</p>
            <p>As the taking up Arms has always dreadful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, it is certain that of two Evils the greateſt is to be avoided, and that it is better to ſuffer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Oppreſſions, than to run to extreme Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
            <p>But my Deſign is to let Mr. <hi>Boſſuet</hi> ſee, that he does not know what he ſays, when he would make it ſo criminal in our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>to approve thoſe who bear Arms to maintain the Goſpel.</hi> As if in this they had done any fooliſh and odious Action. There are ſome Extremities beyond which Chriſtian Morality does not oblige us to carry our Patience. And I think no one can imagine a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Extremity, than when it comes to maſſacring.</p>
            <p>When the firſt War of Religion began in the laſt Age, the Maſſacre of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſy</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:66305:14"/>had given the ſignal to all <hi>France.</hi> There was no longer any place wherein the Proteſtants could be with ſafety. And by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence it was time to make uſe of the Right of Self-preſervation, which no Preſcription, no Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Mighty can ever annihilate.</p>
            <p>But when only the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation or Death of ſome particular Perſons is the concern, as it was in the Reigns of <hi>Francis</hi> the 1ſt, and <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d, then was it a time for Patience, but when the Life of a whole People is in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and in extream ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, then there muſt be a recourſe to extream Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies.</p>
            <p>There may be alſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Circumſtances, when People are not oblig'd to attend the moſt extream Evils before they run to Redreſs them. When the whole Nation ſees the Prince in a Reſolution to extirpate the eſtabliſhed Religion, a ſtop ought to be put at the beginning.</p>
            <p>'Tis therefore that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation cannot be blamed, in their preſent Conduct againſt their King, except it be by thoſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who are full of their Prejudices, or Slaves to the great ones under whom they live, or elſe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant of the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the King had once made himſelf Maſter of the Laws and Religion, it would then have been too late to have ſought for a Remedy.</p>
            <div n="reflections" type="subsection">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:66305:14"/>
               <head>REFLECTIONS UPON THE <hi>Affairs of England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE know very well, my Brethren, that in the Kingdom where you are, 'tis made a point of Honour, and of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to ſpeak all that can be imagin'd cruel and outragious againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and againſt all thoſe il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Perſons who are at the head of that Action which is now brought to paſs in <hi>England.</hi> This great and ſudden Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is at this day the aſtoniſhment of all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> is the execration of Bigots, who diſcharge their fury upon thoſe names which will one day make them tremble.</p>
               <p>Behold (ſay they) the Spirit of your Religion, 'tis Rebellion, a Revolt from Soveraigns, 'tis a black Invaſion of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ordain'd by God.</p>
               <p>I know well that you ought upon this occaſion to have a ſtrict guard o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the meaſures you take, and to conduct yourſelves with a great deal of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and I fear there are ſome amongſt you ill e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough inform'd to give an ill account of an Affair, not only moſt innocent, but even the moſt glorious and the greateſt that has been atchieved for many Ages.</p>
               <p>To convince you of this Truth, you ought to know principally that the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is as inconſiſtent with that of a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, as the Qualification of a <hi>Lutheran</hi> or <hi>Calvinist</hi> is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66305:15"/>with that of a Pope. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more oppoſite to the Fundamental Laws of the State.</p>
               <p n="1">I. It is forbidden under the pain of High Treaſon to perform any Exerciſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Kingdom. How can this be conſiſtent with a Popiſh King, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Maſs to be ſaid pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly in the moſt eminent places of the State, in his Royal-houſes, in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, in the Cities of the Realm.</p>
               <p n="2">II. 'Tis the Crime of High Treaſon in the firſt degree, againſt the State and the Laws, to give reception to Prieſts and Monks within the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. How can this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the condition of a Popiſh King, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for Covents of Monks in his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and every City.</p>
               <p n="3">III. 'Tis a Crime for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Laws, and puniſhable with Death, to acknowledge the Pope to be Head of the Church, and Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt. How can this be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with a King who makes publick profeſſion of recognizing the Pope as Head of the Univerſal Church?</p>
               <p n="4">IV. 'Tis the Law of <hi>England,</hi> that what man ſoever holds correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the Pope in any manner, he ſhall be deemed guilty of High Treaſon. How can this be conſiſtent with the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Papiſt in a King, who believes himſelf o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to receive the Pope's <hi>Nuncio's</hi> in his Court, and to ſend his Ambaſſadors to him?</p>
               <p n="5">V. By the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the King is obliged to make the Oaths of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and Allegiance to be tender'd to all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; by which the King is acknowledged the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Supreme Governour of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and wherein the Superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Pope as well in Spirituals as Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals is expreſly renounced. I would fain know how this can be adjuſted with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66305:15"/>the nature of a Popiſh King? What kind of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is it, whoſe Body is a Proteſtant Church, and whoſe Head is an utter Popiſh King?</p>
               <p n="6">VI. 'Tis a capital Crime by Law to ſollicit People and Subjects to be rec<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> How can this be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Popiſh King who believes himſelf oblig'd in Conſcience to bring back all his Subjects to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, by Threats and Promiſes, by Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Rewards, and Seducements?</p>
               <p n="7">VII. 'Tis a capital Crime in <hi>England</hi> for any perſon to promiſe Obedience to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> How can this agree with the nature of a Popiſh King who calls the Pope Holy Father, and ſubmits him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to him, at leaſt in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals?</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. 'Tis one of the Laws of the Kingdom, that whoever enjoys any publick Office, ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to take the Oath of the Teſt; by which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion is abjur'd and deteſted. But how can this be conſiſtent with the conſtitution of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh King, who poſſeſſes the principal Place of the Kingdom, and therefore ſo publickly embraces and defends the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? There is no end of reciting all the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> from whence there is an abſolute incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency between the being of a King, and the being of a Papiſt in the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>Thus then 'tis evident, that without Injuſtice, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> might declare to the King, that his Religion rendred him uncapable of the Crown.</p>
               <p>It is true, the Crown of <hi>England</hi> is Succeſſive; but according to all Laws, and in all places of the World, he that receives a Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, receives it with all the Charges, which by Law are annexed to it, or he falls from it: He that receives an Eſtate charg'd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66305:16"/>with Rents and Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, muſt perform them, muſt yeild Faith and Hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, if he would enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to poſſeſſion of the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>It is yet more certain, that in Succeſſive Crowns there are certain Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which ought to be in the Succeſſour; if he has them not, he muſt have a Guardian, or a Regent muſt be made, or the Crown devolves to the next fit Heir, who has the Qualifications required by Law.</p>
               <p>The Crown of <hi>England</hi> has a Happineſs above any other Crown in <hi>Europe,</hi> to be ſubject to certain Laws which are above the King; ſo that a perſon who hath not the qualities requiſite, or ſuch as are inconſiſtent with the Laws, is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being admitted to the Crown, tho' he ſhould have the Right of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>All the World knows, that the <hi>French</hi> Popiſh Lords who were in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of <hi>Henry</hi> IV, after the Aſſaſſination of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> III, prayed him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Crown, but in the quality of a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick King, as inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably requiſite to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a King of <hi>France:</hi> They had not the ſame right to diſcourſe at ſuch a rate: for the Kings of <hi>France</hi> had for a long time rais'd themſelves above the Laws; and <hi>Henry</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſuch a State, might have taken it with his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges.</p>
               <p>Beſides it was falſe, that there were any Laws in <hi>France,</hi> which made the quality of a King, and the quality of a Proteſtant to be inconſiſtent; whereas in <hi>England</hi> 'tis apparent, that the condition of a King, and the condition of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt are irreconcilable.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, ſuch was the goodneſs of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, that they would not exclude <hi>James</hi> II. from the Crown; perſwading themſelves that they had laid an inviolable Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon him, religiouſly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66305:16"/>to keep the Oaths made at his Coronation, in preſerving Religion and the Laws as he found them.</p>
               <p>But this Prince ſuffer'd himſelf to be lead by the moſt impudent of Mankind, who lifted him up above the Laws, and made him forget the Devoir of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> which is to Rule according to the Laws. He made a League with a great neighbouring Prince, to ruin the Proteſtant Religion in all <hi>Europe:</hi> He diſpens'd with all the Laws both of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Religion: He made Maſs be ſaid publickly in the three Kingdoms: He inveſted the Papiſts with the principal Offices of State, turning out the Proteſtants: He would conſtrain the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops by corporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to thoſe things which were againſt their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
               <p>And that which is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable Prodigy of Ages, in a Proteſtant Kingdom, he raiſed up a Jeſuite to be a Member of the Council of State, of the Privy-Council, of the Council, in a word, that Governs the whole Kingdom. So a Jeſuite was ſeen Maſter of the Kingdom, Maſter of the Biſhops, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was neceſſary therefore to think of ſecuring Religion and the State; and this the Nation was indiſpenſably o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to. To this purpoſe did ſhe implore the Succour of that Prince, who, now in <hi>England,</hi> is the greateſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Europe:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis againſt him chiefly, that the Country, where you are, diſcharges its Rage; as if he had violated all the Rights of Nature, and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled under Foot the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Conſanguinity.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it appears, that he was called upon by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; this, I ſay, appears by the ſuddenneſs of the Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which was brought to paſs ſo ſoon as it began: The only Princeſs of the Bloud, that was in <hi>England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and the Prince her Husband, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves for him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all the great Men, the Peers, the Cities, the Provinces, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Juſtice of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66305:17"/>his Demands, and ſupported them.</p>
               <p>If this Prince had refus'd to have afforded Succour to the Nation, ſhe would have done the very ſame without him, that ſhe now does un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Banners; and from thence would have unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably followed the ruin of the Monarchy.</p>
               <p>For the State was divided into divers Parties, as it was under <hi>Charles</hi> I: It is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that the Anarchical and Independant Party have once gained the power over it; ſo that we might have ſeen the Nation return to the ſame Eſtate it was under <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and perhaps to a worſe. The King might very poſſibly have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the ſame Miſeries which his Father ſuffer'd.</p>
               <p>The Prince therefore, for the Intereſt of the State, for the Intereſt of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, for his own, and alſo for the King's, could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſe with putting himſelf at the head of an Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which might have been ruin'd, if it had not been go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by ſo great a Soul.</p>
               <p>And then for the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Obligations of Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity, they are meer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances: there are Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations much more indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſable: <hi>He that loveth father or mother more than me, is not worthy of me.</hi> We owe to God, to the Laws, to Religion, more than to our Kindred. It had been a cruel piece of Piety to have ſeen a Church and a Kingdom periſh without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving them, for fear of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending one Perſon with whom we have ſome rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Fleſh and Bloud.</p>
               <p>I know our Enemies will not ſcruple ſaying, that it was not Piety, but Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that gave life to theſe great Motions; which this Great Prince was very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of. But we who are near him, and have known his ſentiments for many Years, are able to witneſs two things; one is, that he is truly touch'd with the Love of God and his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The other is, that he did not undertake this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize till the laſt Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:66305:17"/>
               <p>And we know with the greateſt certainty, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were twenty times refuſed upon the Propoſition which they made; becauſe he always hoped that God would open ſome ſofter Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods to protect Religion from the Oppreſſion which was prepared for it. Thoſe that are near him, can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that there never was a Prince more Zealous, and better affected to the Truth.</p>
               <p>The Succeſs, which God hath given to his Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, may convince us, that he it is, whom God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make uſe of, for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing his great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the True Religion.</p>
               <p>One might further ſay things much more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for Juſtification of this Great Enterprize, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect both to the Nation and the Prince: but time will place them in a better Light, and it ſhall be made known, that thoſe who have ſhed ſo much Bloud, and have had no reſpect to the Laws of Conſanguinity, merit not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard upon their account.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, the Prince has, and always will have a regard to the King, whoſe Deſtiny is ſo much lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for he has no deſign a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Perſon, or againſt his Dignity; he would one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take away from him the means of hurting others, and of hurting himſelf: But this Unfortunate Prince, by following the Inſpirations of that unhappy Genius which hath animated him for ſo many Years, has caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into a Precipiece, and ſaught his Safety by forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Palace and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, without having any juſt cauſe for it.</p>
               <p>It cannot be ſaid with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny truth, that the King of <hi>England</hi> could obſerve, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Conduct of the Prince, or the Lords, or the Biſhops, or the People, any deſign to attack his Perſon, his Life, his Liberty, or his Dignity. On the contrary, every thing was ſo diſpoſed, that Affairs might be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of with the greateſt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Addreſs, which was preſented to the King,
<pb facs="tcp:66305:18"/>after the Prince's arrival, by fourteen or fifteen of the Lords Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal, they promiſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have entreated for a free Parliament, to ſerve him with all their power, and the power of their Friends.</p>
               <p>And in the laſt great Council held <hi>Decemb.</hi> 9th, conſtituted of all that were conſiderable at <hi>London,</hi> it is certain that the King was only askt to call a free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; but this was done with ſuch reſpectful and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Expreſſions, that 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the Nation had no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign againſt the Perſon, or Dignity of the King.</p>
               <p>And the King having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon the meeting of a Parliament upon the 25th of <hi>January,</hi> the Prince accepted of it upon the moſt reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able condition that can be imagined: Which was, that neither his own, nor the King's Army ſhould come within forty Miles of the place where the Parliament ſate.</p>
               <p>Here it appear'd, that the King had no ſincere intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in calling the Parliament, and that it was only to gain time, and to receive the foreign Aſſiſtance which he expected. Theſe Succours failing, and his own Troopes declaring, that they could not fight againſt the Laws and Religion of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; he was reſolv'd ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to play the part of quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Throne: Chooſing, rather not to Reign, than not to Reign over the Laws; and to take the advantage of an odious imputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proteſtants, that they had driven him from his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>But all <hi>Europe</hi> is witneſs to the contrary: and if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after he looſes the Crown, 'tis a loſs for which he can only blame himſelf, having drawn it upon himſelf, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Violation of the Laws, and partly by his Deſertion.</p>
               <p>If there had been any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign violently to drive him from his Throne, why was he ſo ſtopt in his Flight? What an Object is a King Arreſted as a Fugitive! But why was he ſtaid to do him Violence?</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:66305:18"/>
               <p>Was he not honourably entreated to return to his own Palace? Had he not the liberty given, to retire as he was beſt pleaſed?</p>
               <p>I queſtion not, but all this ſhall be reflected upon us with the moſt malevolent Influences; for 'tis a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon thing with the Papiſm in its rage, to take hold of all that may any way ſerve its Revenge.</p>
               <p>But be wiſe, and Adore the profound Judgments of God. You ſee in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, the firſt blow to the ruin of Popery, which we have propoſed apparently near, out of the Prophecies of the <hi>New Teſtament:</hi> This great and ſurprizing Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution will without doubt draw others after it, which ſhall be no leſs conſiderable. The Empire of Antichriſt hath not received ſo terrible a check ſince the laſt Age: it rouls down to its Fall, and God viſibly puſhes it upon the Precipiece.</p>
               <p>Keep ſilence then, my Brethren, but do not ſuffer your ſelves to be carried down the ſtream of Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages againſt him whom God hath choſen for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of his great Work.</p>
               <p>Remember the Injuſtice which the Papiſts have been guilty of at this time: To violate Laws, which ought to have been moſt invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, to break their Oaths, to trample under Foot the moſt ſacred Engagements, to ſeize upon the Miſerable, and force them to Abjurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to throw them into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to ſend them to Gallies, to Baniſh them, and confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Goods: This is all good and lawful for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>But to maintain the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Religion by main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Laws, and to repreſs the Enterprizes of thoſe that would violate them, this is an horrible Attempt, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Action.</p>
               <p>Is not this to weigh Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in unequal Balances?</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>January 1, 1689.</date> 
                     <hi>With the Priviledge of our Lords the States. Rotterdam,</hi> at the Houſe of <hi>Abr. Acher,</hi> near the <hi>Bourſe.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:66305:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>J. Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. A Diſcourſe concerning the Nature, Power, and Proper Effects of the Preſent Conventions in both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, called by the Prince of <hi>Orange. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. A Political Conference between <hi>Aulicus</hi> a Courtier, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> a Country-man, and <hi>Civicus</hi> a Citizen, Clearing the Original of Civil Government, the Powers and Duties of Soveraigns and Subjects, in a familiar and plain Way, which may be underſtood by every ordinary Capacity. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Liberty of Conſcience Explicated and Vindicated, and the Juſt Limits betwixt it and Authority Sacred and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Cleared. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. The Triumphs of Grace: or, the laſt Words and Edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Death of the Lady <hi>Margaret de la Muſſe,</hi> a Noble <hi>French</hi> Lady, Aged only Sixteen Years. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
